Guide to the Flürscheim Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Flürscheim family papers
1743-1913
MS 1582
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(1 box, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, financial and business records, genealogical tables, marriage and birth certificates, and photographs.
Flürscheim family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Charles Strauss, 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, financial and business records, genealogical tables, marriage and birth certificates, and photographs.
Emigration and immigration; Families; Jews, German; Germany -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Diaries; Flürscheim, Hermann Adolph; Flürscheim family
- Genealogical tables of the Flürscheim family, 1743-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Passport issued to Jacob Moses Flürscheim, 1798 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to unidentified person from Schweizer, 1802 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Diary of an unidentified young man (possibly Adolph Michael Flürscheim), 1803 May-1803 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fragment of a diary, 1803 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
- School certificate awarded to member of Flürscheim family, 1813-1814 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Sales contract for home of Wilhelm Salomon Haas, 1815 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bills of exchange of the business firm of M. M. Flürscheim & Son, 1822-1823 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Certificate granting permission to Bernhard Flürscheim to take the oath of an "israelite" citizen as a merchant of Frankfurt, 1836 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from A. Zimmerman to M. M. Flürscheim & Son, 1840 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Notebook listing events in the Bernhard Flürscheim family, 1842 December-1899 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Amts=blatt der freien Stadt Frankfurt announcing the marriage of Bernhard Flürscheim to Sara Gunderscheim and the birth of Hermann Adolph Flürscheim, 1849 June-1851 August (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Partnership agreement between Bernhard Adolph Flürscheim and Moritz Adolph Flürscheim, 1850 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Birth certificate(s) of Hermann Adolph Flürscheim, 1851 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notebook of Hermann A. Flürscheim containing a diary, lock of hair, and assorted notes, 1867-1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Certificate of good conduct issued to apprentice Hermann A. Flürscheim, 1868 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Permission of Sara Flürscheim allowing her son Hermann A. Flürscheim to enter the Royal Military Service, 1868 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Permission for Hermann A. Flürscheim to leave his apprenticeship, 1869 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Page from a notebook giving date of departure from Berlin and arrival in America of Hermann A. Flürscheim, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Certificate of discharge releasing Hermann A. Flürscheim from his Prussian citizenship, 1874 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Unidentified wedding toast, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Newsclipping pertaining to a legatee of the estate of Hermann A. Flürscheim, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous note, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photographs
  - Hermann Flürscheim, 1878, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bella Goldsmith Flürscheim, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Marriage certificates, 1843 January 7, 1849 May 20, 1876 January 2 (Box 2)